There is one thing that Americans are
really good at and that is small talk
conversations. Are you good at small
talk in English? Well, never fear. In
today's lesson, you are going to learn
the top 10 most common small talk
questions and how to answer them, plus
three bonus questions at the end of
today's lesson. You will never be stuck
uh frozen with nothing to say in a small
talk conversation in English again. And
like always, I have created a free PDF
worksheet for you with all of today's 10
+ three bonus small talk questions and
answers so that you're never frozen
and not knowing what to say. The next
time that you have a conversation, it's
going to be no problem for you. Plus, to
help you really master these small talk
questions and answers, I have included
inside the PDF worksheet a free speaking
practice. You can download this speaking
practice. Listen to my voice saying
these questions and answers and repeat
them out loud with me. This is the
number one way to be able to actually
improve your pronunciation and your
speaking skills. When you are repeating
or shadowing with someone else, it is a
lot easier to speak like them, to
remember what you're saying, and to
actually master the phrases that you
want to learn. So, how can you get this
free PDF worksheet plus bonus speaking
practice? All you have to do is click on
the link in the description, enter your
name and email address, and voila, just
like that, the free worksheet and bonus
speaking practice will land in your
email inbox. And something even cooler
is that you never need to sign up for my
free PDF worksheets again. You just sign
up one time and I will continue to send
them to you every single week. It is my
gift to you. So, click on the link in
the description to get the worksheet and
the speaking practice and get started.
All right, let's start with today's
lesson. The first three small talk
questions are just general, the most
commonly used. Let's imagine the
scenario. You are walking through your
neighborhood and your neighbor is
watering her plants. You want to say
something to her. What should you say?
Here you go. How's it going? Great. This
is an excellent question and extremely
commonly used with all ages. And your
neighbor might say, "Pretty good. How
about you?" Or maybe your neighbor will
add a little more and say something
like, "Pretty good. Just trying to keep
these plants alive. how about you? Or
you could ask, hey, what have you been
up to? And your neighbor might reply,
oh, not much. Mostly working and
spending time with the kids. What about
you? This final question that is often
asked in return could be asked two ways.
They might ask, "What about you?" or
"How about you?" And it is really just
returning the question to you. It's
bouncing the ball back in your court and
making you have to answer the same
question. So, that's why I want you to
practice these answers as well. Or our
third question you might ask your
neighbor as they're watering their
plants is, "How's everything been?"
How's everything been? Now, there
doesn't have to be a big to-do in their
life, like a new wedding or going on a
big trip, in order for you to ask this
question. It just means, "How is your
life going? How's everything been? And
your neighbor might say, "It's been
good. Busy as always, but no complaints.
How about you?" And here it's your turn
to answer. All right. The next two small
talk questions have to do with your
health. This is a common small talk
question. So, let's imagine the scenario
where you're going to meet a friend at a
cafe and you knew that your friend had a
cold recently and so you're just trying
to make some small talk. You might ask,
"Are you feeling any better today?" Now,
notice in a lot of these questions, the
G at the end of ing, feeling, is cut
off. Are you feeling any better today?
This just makes it more personal, more
relatable. It's not rude to use this
type of pronunciation with all ages.
You're welcome to use this, and it's
just a comfortable way to speak with
other people. and your friend might say,
"Yeah, much better. I just have a little
cough now, but I'm feeling much better.
Thanks for asking." This final phrase,
"Thanks for asking," is a really kind
way to show the other person that you
appreciate that they remember. You
appreciate that they care. Thanks for
asking. Let's imagine that instead of
your friend having a cold, it was your
friend's son who had a cold. You might
ask instead, "How's your son doing?" And
your friend might say, "Oh, yeah, he had
a cold for forever, but he's finally
getting better. I'm so glad. Thanks for
asking." You could use this question in
a more general sense if you asked,
"How's your family doing?" And this
could be just generally asking, "How are
your family doing? How what are they up
to these days?" It's not necessarily
about their health, but if you said,
"How's your son doing?" in the context
of him previously being sick. It's about
his health, but you're welcome to also
use this generally. How's your family
doing? Great question. The next two
small talk questions are about work and
daily life. Let's imagine the scenario
that you're at the grocery store and you
run into a co-orker who hasn't been at
the office lately because they've been
on a trip. Well, what can you say in
this scenario? You might ask about their
trip and ask, "When did you get back
into town?" Now, this is just a
logistics question. It's not saying,
"How was your trip? Tell me all about
it." Maybe you have a formal
relationship together and you don't want
to get into the details, but asking this
type of question just acknowledges that
you knew they were gone and you want to
make small talk. So, you could ask that,
"When did you get back into town?" And
your coworker might say, "I just got
back a couple days ago. The jet lag has
been really tough this time. Okay, great
answer. And because your coworker hasn't
been in the office lately or been at
work lately, your coworker might ask
you, "How's work going?" "How's work
going?" And you might reply, "It's been
such a busy week, but I had a really
relaxing weekend, so I feel much more
refreshed now." [laughter]
This is a common small talk question.
How's work going? And if you don't want
to talk about work, you could just say,
"It's going fine. It's fine. Nothing
much to report. You can answer in kind
of that evasive way if you want. That's
part of small talk as well. But you're
welcome to share a couple more details.
How's work going?" "Oh, yeah. I just
finished up this really big project. It
was so cool and I'm really glad that we
finished it on the deadline." Okay.
Okay. Well, that kind of gives the other
person an in to be able to ask questions
about it if they want and it could start
a bigger conversation. Who knows? Or it
might just be small talk. The next two
small talk questions are about weekends
and free time. So, let's imagine that it
is Monday morning and you're at the
office getting a cup of coffee at your
office's coffee station, coffee pot, and
your colleague walks up. [gasps] What
should you say? freeze and panic. Nope.
[laughter]
Because of this lesson, you're going to
know exactly what to say. You could say
something like this. Hey, what'd you do
this weekend? Great question. And your
colleague might answer, "H, not too
much. I just saw some friends and then
caught up on all the chores I needed to
do." What about you? Here they are
throwing the question back at you. What
about you? How about you? So, make sure
that you are prepared to answer. If this
scenario happens later in the week,
let's say a Friday, you might ask your
colleague this. Got any plans for the
weekend? Got any plans for the weekend?
This is a tricky question to ask. You
need to make sure that you ask it in
this casual way. Notice that I kind of
abbreviated the beginning of this
question. I didn't say, "Do you have any
plans for this weekend?" Instead, I
said, "Got any plans for this weekend?"
got any plans for the weekend or this
weekend? This is important because if
you said this a little more seriously, a
little more formally, do you have any
plans for this weekend? How does that
feel to you? Do you think the other
person would think, is Vanessa asking me
if I want to spend time with her this
weekend?
This could be a little complicated. So,
make sure when you ask this question,
you ask it in this informal way. Hey,
got any plans this weekend? really
casual, maybe a little shrug. You're not
seriously asking them, "Do you have any
plans for this weekend?"
Just got any plans for the weekend? And
you could answer or your colleague might
answer, "Not really. My mom's coming
into town on Sunday, but I don't have
any plans for the rest of the weekend.
Probably just take it easy." Great.
Okay. This is a casual way to answer.
And of course, if you feel like the
other person is being a little bit too
uh uncomfortable asking you directly, do
you have any plans for the weekend? And
you don't want to tell them, you don't
have to tell them anything. You could
just say, eh, not really. How about you?
You can just throw it right back at
them. If you don't feel like sharing
anything personal, our final small talk
question, plus three bonus questions,
are all about the most common small talk
topic ever. It is the weather. No matter
who you're talking to, a random person
you don't know, a colleague, a friend, a
neighbor, the weather is a safe topic
and it affects everybody, right? So,
it's not extremely boring. It could be
boring, but we can make it interesting
with these questions. These are
questions I use all the time, so I want
to make sure that you can use them as
well. So, let's imagine this scenario.
Let's imagine you're waiting at the bus
stop and there's someone beside you who
you don't know and it is extremely cold.
It is unusually cold for this time of
year. What can you say? Can you believe
this weather? [laughter] And the other
person might say, "I know. It just seems
like winter is never going to end.
Can you believe this weather?" Wonderful
question. Or you might say, "Gh, the
weather has been so unpredictable
lately. It's hot one day, cold the next.
What am I supposed to wear? I don't
know." [laughter]
And the other person might say, "I know.
I just wear my winter coat in the
morning, and by the afternoon, I only
have a t-shirt on. [laughter] This is
something that affects us all." Well,
let's imagine that the weather is
actually okay. Goodish weather. What can
you say? H it's such a nice day today,
isn't it? And here this question at the
end, we call that a tag question because
you're just tagging it on at the end and
you're hoping that the other person will
give some kind of reply. It's such a
nice day today, isn't it? Maybe the
other person will say, I know it is. I
can't believe it. [laughter] Or maybe
the other person will just say, yeah,
okay, maybe they didn't want to have a
conversation. But this type of small
talk back and forth is really common in
the US. Let's imagine you're at the bus
stop and it is pouring down rain. It's
kind of an inconvenient type of weather
to have when you're waiting for the bus.
Hopefully, there's a little shelter you
can wait under. You might say something
like this. I heard it's supposed to rain
all weekend.
Unfortunate. Maybe you need rain where
you live. Or maybe it's just too much
rain. If you said this to someone or if
someone said this to you, how can you
reply, "I heard it's supposed to rain
all weekend." Well, you can probably
commiserate with them. This word
commiserate means you're going to
complain together. [laughter] So, you
might say, "H, it's been raining for so
long. I wish it would just stop." You
are commiserating together about the bad
weather. Well, there you have it. 10
common small talk questions and answers
that I use all the time and you can too.
Oh, plus three bonuses. I hope you
enjoyed those. Don't forget to download
the free PDF worksheet for today's
lesson. This includes all of today's
important small talk questions and
answers, plus the bonus speaking
practice. In this speaking practice, I'm
going to be saying out loud each of the
questions and answers, and then I'm
going to be pausing to give you a chance
to repeat exactly what I said. This type
of repeating practice is the best way to
remember what you've learned. You're
using it right away. So, don't miss out
on this speaking practice. All you need
to do is click on the link in the
description, enter your name and email
address, and voila, just like that, the
free PDF worksheet and speaking practice
will land in your email inbox. It is my
gift to you. So, click on the link in
the description and don't wait, start
speaking. Use this. [laughter] Have a
small talk conversations wherever you go
or even just with me in the speaking
practice. And now I have a question for
you. I want to know got any plans for
this weekend? Let me know in the
comments what your plans are. I can't
wait to read them and learn more about
you. Thank you so much for learning
English with me. And I'll see you again
next Friday for a new lesson here on my
YouTube channel. Bye. But wait, do you
want more? I recommend watching this
video next where you will learn 10
everyday expressions that I use about my
evening routine, including what to say
when you come home from work completely
tired. What should you say?